This is Revolution 2.0.
هذه ثورة 2‪.‬0
No one was a hero. No one was a hero.
لم يكن هناك بطل .. .. لم يكن هناك بطل
Because everyone was a hero.
لأن الجميع كانوا أبطالا
Everyone has done something.
كلٌ منا شارك بشيء
We all use Wikipedia.
كلنا نستخدم موقع الويكيبيديا
If you think of the concept of Wikipedia
لو فكرنا في طريقة عمل ويكيبيديا
where everyone is collaborating on content,
كل شخص بيقوم باضافة محتوى ولو يسير
and at the end of the day
وفي النهاية
you've built the largest encyclopedia in the world.
استطاعت ويكيبيديا أن تكون أكبر موسوعة في العالم
From just an idea that sounded crazy,
من مجرد فكرة مجنونة
you have the largest encyclopedia in the world.
إلى أكبر موسوعة في العالم
And in the Egyptian revolution,
وفي الثورة المصرية
the Revolution 2.0,
ثورة ٢.٠
everyone has contributed something,
قام كل واحد منا بأداء
small or big. They contributed something --
دور سواء كان كبيرا أو صغيرا
to bring us
الجميع شارك ليخرجوا لنا
one of the most inspiring stories
واحد من أكثر القصص إلهاما
in the history of mankind
في تاريخ الثورات البشرية
It was actually really inspiring
كان ملهما
to see all these Egyptians completely changing.
أن نرى كل هؤلاء المصريين يتغيرون
If you look at the scene,
لو نظرنا لوضع مصر
Egypt, for 30 years, had been in a downhill --
في الثلاثين عاما الماضية فسنجد أن الوضع من سيء
going into a downhill.
لأسوأ
Everything was going bad.
كل شيء بمجمله كان يسير إلى الأسوأ
Everything was going wrong.
وفي الاتجاه الخاطئ
We only ranked high when it comes to poverty,
في التصنيف العالمي كنا نحتل المراكز الأولى في الفقر
corruption,
الفساد
lack of freedom of speech,
وغياب حرية الرأي الحقيقية
lack of political activism.
وكذلك غياب النشاط السياسي
Those were the achievements
كانت هذه هي إنجازات
of our great regime.
نظامنا السابق
Yet, nothing was happening.
ولكن لم يكن هناك من يعترض من المصريين
And it's not because people were happy
وهذا ليس لأنهم سعداء
or people were not frustrated.
أو لم يكونوا غاضبين
In fact, people were extremely frustrated.
على العكس كان الشعب غاضبا مما يحدث حوله
But the reason why everyone was silent
ولكن السبب الرئيسي للصمت
is what I call the psychological barrier of fear.
كان هو حاجز الخوف النفسي
Everyone was scared.
كان الجميع خائفا
Not everyone. There were actually a few brave Egyptians
أستدرك لم يكن الجميع لأن مجموعة قليلة من المصريين العظماء
that I have to thank for being so brave --
ممن يستحقون الشكر كانوا في منتهى الشجاعة
going into protests as a couple of hundred,
كانوا يخرجون إلى المظاهرات بأعداد قليلة
getting beaten up and arrested.
ويتم ضربهم والقبض عليهم
But in fact, the majority were scared.
ولكن الحقيقة أن الأغلبية كانت خائفة
Everyone did not want really
كانت الأغلبية تخشى الوقوع
to get in trouble.
في مشكلة مع النظام
A dictator cannot live without the force.
لا يستطيع الدكتاتور أن يعيش بدون استخدام القوة
They want to make people live in fear.
يريدون أن يعيش الناس في خوف
And that psychological barrier of fear
وكانت خطة حاجز الخوف النفسي
had worked for so many years,
ناجحة ولسنوات طويلة
and here comes the Internet,
وحينما جاءت الإنترنت
technology, BlackBerry, SMS.
والتقنية بصفة عامة كالرسائل القصيرة والبلاكبيري
It's helping all of us to connect.
كانت تساعدنا على التواصل
Platforms like YouTube, Twitter, Facebook
مواقع مثل اليوتيوب والفيسبوك وتويتر
were helping us a lot
ساعدتنا بشكل كبير
because it basically gave us the impression that, "Wow, I'm not alone.
أهميتها كانت أن الواحد منا بدخوله على الإنترنت يشعر أنه ليس غاضبا لوحده
There are a lot of people who are frustrated."
هناك الكثير ممن هم غير راضون عن الأوضاع
There are lots of people who actually share the same dream.
هناك الكثير ممن يشاركون بعضهم البعض نفس الأحلام
There are lots of people who care about their freedom.
هناك الكثير ممن يهتمون بحريتهم
They probably have the best life in the world.
لديهم على الأغلب أفضل حياه في العالم
They are living in happiness. They are living in their villas.
يعيشون في سعادة.. يعيشون فيه فيللهم
They are happy. They don't have problems.
قد يعيشون حياة رائعة في بيوتهم ولا يعانون من المشاكل
But they are still feeling the pain of the Egyptian.
ولكن كان العامل المشترك هو إحساسنا بآلام المصريين
A lot of us, we're not really happy
الكثير منا كان يشعر بالحزن
when we see a video of an Egyptian man
حينما يرى مصريا
who's eating the trash
مصريا يأكل من القمامة في الشارع
while others are stealing
في نفس الوقت الذي يسرق فيه الآخرين المليارات
billions of Egyptian pounds
الآخرين المليارات
from the wealth of the country.
من ثروات الشعب المصري
The Internet has played a great role,
ساهمت الإنترنت بدور كبير
helping these people to speak up their minds,
في مساعدة هؤلاء في التعبير عن آرائهم بحرية
to collaborate together, to start thinking together.
للتفكير والتعاون مع بعضهم البعض
It was an educational campaign.
كانت الإنترنت مثل حملة من حملات التوعية
Khaled Saeed was killed
قُتل خالد سعيد
in June 2010.
في يونيو 2010
I still remember the photo.
وصورته التي لازلت أتذكر كل تفاصيلها
The photo was horrible.
كانت صورة مرعبة
He was tortured,
تم تعذيبه
brutally tortured to death.
تم تعذيبه بوحشية للموت
But then what was the answer of the regime?
ولكن ماذا قال النظام؟
"He choked on a pile of hash" --
خالد مات لأنه بلع لفافة بانجو
that was their answer:
كانت هذه إجابتهم
"He's a criminal.
خالد مجرم
He's someone who escaped from all these bad things."
وهو هارب من العدالة
But people did not relate to this.
ولكننا لم نصدقهم
People did not believe this.
الناس لم تصدقهم
Because of the Internet, the truth prevailed
وبسبب الإنترنت ظهرت الحقيقة
and everyone knew the truth.
الجميع علمها
And everyone started to think that "this guy could be my brother."
وجميعنا شعر أن خالد كان من الممكن أن يكون أخ لنا
He was a middle-class guy.
شاب من الطبقة المتوسطة
His photo was remembered by all of us.
صورته في أذهاننا
A page was created.
تم إنشاء الصفحة
An anonymous administrator
والأدمن المجهول
was basically inviting people to join the page,
بدأ في دعوة الجميع للانضمام للصفحة
and there was no plan.
ولم يكن هناك أي خطة
"What are we going to do?" "I don't know."
ماذا سنفعل من أجل إرجاع حق خالد؟ لم تكن هناك إجابة
In a few days, tens of thousands of people there --
ولكن في أيام قليلة انضم عشرات الآلاف للصفحة
angry Egyptians
مصريون غاضبون
who were asking the ministry of interior affairs,
انضموا للصفحة ليقولوا لوزارة الداخلية
"Enough.
كفى
Get those who killed this guy.
نريد منكم محاسبة المسؤولين عن قتل خالد سعيد
To just bring them to justice."
وتقديمهم للعدالة
But of course, they don't listen.
ولكن النظام بالطبع لم يكن ليستمع لمطالبنا
It was an amazing story --
كان من المذهل
how everyone started feeling the ownership.
كيف كان كل من في الصفحة من أعضاء يتصرفون من منطلق المسؤولية عن الصفحة
Everyone was an owner in this page.
كل واحد كان يتصرف كأنه صاحب الصفحة
People started contributing ideas.
الأفكار بدأت في الظهور على الصفحة لنصرة القضية
In fact, one of the most ridiculous ideas
فمثلا فكرة من الأفكار المجنونة التي تم اقتراحها على الصفحة
was, "Hey, let's have a silent stand.
هي فكرة الوقفات الصامتة
Let's get people to go in the street,
لندعو الناس للخروج للشارع
face the sea, their back to the street,
ظهرهم للشارع ووجهم للبحر
dressed in black, standing up silently for one hour,
مرتدين الملابس السوداء , ولمدة ساعة دون الحديث مع بعضهم البعض
doing nothing and then just leaving,
لا يفعلون شيء.. ثم يغادرون
going back home."
والعودة إلى بيوتهم
For some people, that was like, "Wow, silent stand.
وكانت الفكرة مدعاة للسخرية من الكثير حتى أن أحدهم قال: النهاردة الوقفة صامتة
And next time it's going to be vibration."
وغدا ستكون وقفة فايبريشن
People were making fun of the idea.
كان الناس يسخرون من الفكرة
But actually when people went to the street --
ولكن الناس نزلت إلى الشارع
the first time it was thousands of people
لكن حينما خرج الآلاف
in Alexandria --
ولأول مرة في الإسكندرية
it felt like -- it was amazing. It was great
كان شعورا مذهلا
because it connected people from the virtual world,
فلأول مرة يلتقي الناس من العالم الافتراضي
bringing them to the real world,
إلى العالم الحقيقي
sharing the same dream,
حلمهم واحد
the same frustration, the same anger,
غضبهم واحد
the same desire for freedom.
كلهم باحثون عن الحرية
And they were doing this thing.
وكانو يحققون هذا الحلم
But did the regime learn anything? Not really.
ولكن هل استفاد النظام شيئا؟ على العكس
They were actually attacking them.
كانوا يتعاملون مع الشباب والبنات بقسوة
despite the fact of how peaceful these guys were --
رغم أنهم يقفون بشكل سلمي وبسيط على الكورنيش
they were not even protesting.
لم يكونوا يتظاهرون
And things had developed
واستمرت نشاطات الصفحة
until the Tunisian revolution.
حتى ظهرت الثورة التونسية
This whole page was, again,
كلنا خالد سعيد كانت من بدايتها
managed by the people.
تدار من قبل أعضائها
In fact, the anonymous admin job
كان دور الأدمن المجهول
was to collect ideas,
هو جمع الأفكار
help people to vote on them
ومساعدة الأعضاء على التصويت
and actually tell them what they are doing.
وإعلان نتائج التصويت
People were taking shots and photos;
الأعضاء كانوا هم من يقوم بتسجيل الفيديوهات والتفاط الصور
people were reporting violations of human rights in Egypt;
ونشر انتهاكات حقوق الإنسان في مصر
people were suggesting ideas,
كان الأعضاء هم من يقترح الأفكار
they were actually voting on ideas,
والتصويت عليها
and then they were executing the ideas; people were creating videos.
وتنفيذها; الناس كانت تصور الفيديوهات
Everything was done by the people to the people,
كل ما حدث كان من الناس إلى الناس
and that's the power of the Internet.
وهذه هي قوة الإنترنت
There was no leader.
لم يكن هناك قائدا
The leader was everyone on that page.
القائد كان هو كل شخص في الصفحة
The Tunisian experiment, as Amir was saying,
الثورة التونسية
inspired all of us, showed us that there is a way.
ألهمتنا وجعلتنا نشعر أن هناك أمل وأنه يمكننا تحقيق حلمنا
Yes we can. We can do it.
نعم نستطيع .. يمكن أن نفعلها
We have the same problems;
لدينا نفس المشاكل
we can just go in the streets.
والحل هو الذهاب للشارع
And when I saw the street on the 25th,
وحينما رأيت الشارع يوم 25 يناير
I went back and said,
رجعت للبيت وكتبت
"Egypt before the 25th
مصر قبل 25 يناير
is never going to be Egypt after the 25th.
لن تكون مصر بعد 25 يناير
The revolution is happening.
الثورة تحدث
This is not the end,
25 يناير لن يكون النهاية
this is the beginning of the end."
لكنه سيكون بداية النهاية
I was detained on the 27th night.
تم اختطافي ليلة 27 يناير
Thank God I announced the locations and everything.
بعد الإعلان عن أماكن التجمعات في جمعة الغضب
But they detained me.
ولكنهم إختطفوني
And I'm not going to talk about my experience, because this is not about me.
ولن أتحدث عن تجربتي الشخصية لأن الثورة لم تكن ثورة شخص
I was detained for 12 days,
كنت معتقلا لمدة 12 يوما
blindfolded, handcuffed.
كنت طوالها مغمم العينين ومكبل اليدين
And I did not really hear anything. I did not know anything.
لم أكن أعرف ما يحدث في الخارج
I was not allowed to speak with anyone.
ولم يكن من الممكن أن أتحدث مع أحد
And I went out.
وحينما خرجت
The next day I was in Tahrir.
ذهبت مباشرة في اليوم التالي إلى التحرير
Seriously, with the amount of change I had noticed in this square,
وذهلت مما رأيت من تغير في المصريين
I thought it was 12 years.
شعرت أنني قضيت 12 عاما
I never had in my mind
لم أكن لأتخيل يوما
to see this Egyptian,
لأرى هذا المصري العظيم على حقيقته
The fear is no longer fear.
الخوف لم يعد موجودا
It's actually strength -- it's power.
بل وتحول إلى قوة
People were so empowered.
كان الجميع مفعما بالإرادة
It was amazing how everyone was so empowered
من المذهل كيف كان الناس مفعمين بالإرادة
and now asking for their rights.
ويطالبون بحقوقهم
Completely opposite.
على غير المتوقع
Extremism became tolerance.
التطرف اختفى وحل بدلا منه السماحة
Who would [have] imagined before the 25th,
من كان يتخيل قبل 25 يناير
if I tell you that hundreds of thousands of Christians are going to pray
أن مئات الآلاف من المسيحيين سيصلون
and tens of thousands of Muslims are going to protect them,
ليحميهم عشرات الآلاف من المسلمين
and then hundreds of thousands of Muslims are going to pray
وأن مئات الآلاف من المسلمين سيصلون
and tens of thousands of Christians are going to protect them --
ليحميهم عشرات الآلاف من المسيحيين
this is amazing.
كان هذا رائعا
All the stereotypes
كل الأكاذيب
that the regime was trying to put on us
التي كان يروجها النظام
through their so-called propaganda, or mainstream media,
من خلال آلته الإعلامية المضللة
are proven wrong.
ثبت خطؤها
This whole revolution showed us
هذه الثورة أظهرت
how ugly such a regime was
كم كان هذا النظام مقززا
and how great and amazing
وكيف كان عظيم و مذهل
the Egyptian man, the Egyptian woman,
كل مصري و كل مصرية
how simple and amazing these people are
وكم كان هذا الشعب عظيما وبسيطا
whenever they have a dream.
حينما يكون توفر لديه الحلم
When I saw that,
حينما رأيت ذلك
I went back and I wrote on Facebook.
رجعت من التحرير إلى البيت وكتبت على الفيسبوك
And that was a personal belief,
وكان إيمانا شخصيا
regardless of what's going on,
بغض النظر عن الأحداث الجارية
regardless of the details.
بغض النظر عن التفاصيل
I said that, "We are going to win.
"سننتصر"
We are going to win because we don't understand politics.
سننتصر لأننا لا نفهم في سياستهم
We're going to win because we don't play their dirty games.
سننتصر لأننا لا نفهم في ألعابهم القذرة
We're going to win because we don't have an agenda.
سننتصر لأننا ليس لدينا أجندة
We're going to win because the tears that come from our eyes
سننتصر لأن الدموع تخرج ليس من عيوننا
actually come from our hearts.
بل من قلوبنا
We're going to win because we have dreams.
سننتصر لأن لدينا حلما
We're going to win because we are willing to stand up for our dreams."
سننتصر لأننا سنحارب من أجل أحلامنا
And that's actually what happened. We won.
وهذا ما حدث انتصرنا
And that's not because of anything,
ولم يكن انتصارنا لأي سبب
but because we believed in our dream.
سوى إيمان كل منا بالحلم
The winning here is not
النصر هنا
the whole details of what's going to happen in the political scene.
لا يقصد به النصر السياسي
The winning is the winning of the dignity
النصر هنا هو نصر الكرامة
of every single Egyptian.
لكل مصري
Actually, I had this taxi driver telling me,
أتذكر سائق التاكسي الذي قال لي:
"Listen, I am breathing freedom.
أنا أتنفس حرية
I feel that I have dignity
أشعر أن لدي كرامة
that I have lost for so many years."
كنت قد فقدتها منذ زمن طويل
For me that's winning,
هذا هو الانتصار الحقيقي
regardless of all the details.
بغض النظر عن التفاصيل
My last word to you is a statement I believe in,
آخر كلمة أقولها لكم هي مقولة
which Egyptians have proven to be true,
أثبت المصريون صحتها
that the power of the people
قوة الشعب
is much stronger than the people in power.
أقوى بكثير من قوة الذين يحكمون الشعب
Thanks a lot.
شكرا
(Applause)
(تصفيق)